" The three mothers . "
I do not know what price I shall have to pay for breaking what we alchemists call silentium .
The life experiences of our colleagues should warn us not to upset laymen by imposing our knowledge upon them .
I , varelli , an architect living in London , met the three mothers ...
And designed and built for them three dwelling places .
One in Rome , one in New York and the third in freiburg , Germany .
I failed to discover until too late ...
That from those three locations ...
The three mothers rule the world with sorrow , tears and darkness .
Mater suspiriorum , " the mother of sighs , " and the oldest of the three ,
lives in freiburg .
Mater lacrimarum , " the mother of tears , "
and the most beautiful of the sisters , holds rule in Rome .
Mater tenebrarum , " the mother of darkness , "
who is the youngest and cruelest of the three , controls New York
and I built their horrible houses .
The repositories of all their filthy secrets .
Those so-called mothers are actually wicked stepmothers ,
incapable of creating life-infamous !
Thereby giving these creatures a single , yet terrifying name .
In effect , however , those three were sisters as well as mothers ,
just as there are three muses , three graces , three fates and three furies .
The land upon which the three houses have been constructed ...
Will eventually become deathly and plague-ridden ,
so much so that the area all around will reek horribly .
And that is the first key to the mothers ' secret .
Truly , the primary key .
The second key to the poisonous secret of the three sisters ...
Is hidden in the cellar under their houses .
There you can find both the picture and the name of the sister living in that house .
This is the location of the second key .
The third key can be found under the soles of your shoes .
There is the third key .
My dear brother Mark -
The second key is hidden in the cellar .
Good evening . I 'd like to talk to you about that book .
Ah ? Which one ?
The one that you sold me .
The three mothers .
Have you read it ?
Some of it .
Is that story just made up , or is there some truth to it ?
Did it upset you ?
It 's nothing more than a book written by some alchemist .
Lots of books have been written about houses of the damned .
The bagheria villa of monsters , near palermo ,
the house of peacocks in Brussels ,
the salamander Maison in France .
Some people think of these books as pure fantasy .
Others believe every word .
Women are usually the worst readers of such stuff ,
or the best , if you prefer .
They want very much to believe .
Not really .
That book mentions a horrible odor , for example .
And all around here there 's a very strange , bittersweet smell .
They say that comes from the cake factory . It 's been here as long as I have .
Does it bother you ?
You 'll get used to it after a while .
You 'll stop noticing it .
That 's not the only weird coincidence .
If you read the book-there are mysterious parts in that book ,
but the only true mystery is that our very lives ...
Are governed by dead people .
Good night .
[ Cat meows I
the second key is hidden in the cellar .
She 's been nosing around .
We 'll have to hide everything right away .
Yes . We 'd better get it all out of sight .
Be careful though . He doesn 't want anything changed .
J "
Ju
This is the famous " va , pensiero chorus . "
Finale
ju
Terza parte .
From giuseppe verdi 's nabucco .
J "
Ju [ Chorus swells I
" My dear brother Mark ,
as you know , here in New York ,
I 've been living in a rather old building for quite some time . "
Ju
Ju [ Chorus swells I
J
Excuse me .
I want to go someplace else .
Via dei bagni , number 49 .
What a strange smell .
Sickly sweet .
What 's wrong ?
Nothing .
Angels .
Demons .
J-27 . All of that ?
Yes .
Hey .
[ Wom an how ? !
No .
Yes .
I 'm looking for an old book .
Well , what book would you like ?
Its title is the three mothers .
Yes . The three mothers .
Why , it should be there , right behind you .
Thanks .
" This book is neither fictional , nor a work of imagination .
It includes instead fragments of a diary ...
Which I discovered among the personal papers of a friend ,
an architect and highly respected alchemist by the name of varelli .
Varelli disappeared under mysterious circumstances many years ago . "
" This diary may help clear up the reasons for his strange death .
Since it was written in Latin , we 've decided to publish it in that form . "
Sara .
Closing time .
Oh , really ? Where ?
It 's out in the back . I think it 's -
it 's about the relationship between zen buddhism and -
Sir ?
Pardon me .
Sir , excuse me .
I can 't find the way out .
The other door .
The book !
No ! No !
Here ! No !
I think we should have a meeting of the condominium .
Yes . We have to put a stop to it .
What floor ?
The fourth .
Hmm .
No .
Anything I can do for you ?
I 'm afraid .
I 'm afraid to be left alone .
All right . I 've got nothing to do for the next couple of hours .
I could keep you company if you like .
What do you do , Sara ? Study or work ?
I 'm a music student . What about you ?
Oh , I 'm in sports . I 'm a sportswriter for television .
- May I ask you a strange question ? - How strange ?
Have you ever heard of the three sisters ?
You mean those black singers ? No .
I 'm talking about mythology .
The triad . Hold on .
If you 're talking about spooks and stuff , I don 't believe in any of that .
How can you be so sure ? I don 't believe in such things . That 's all .
And without any philosophical discussion .
And what do you believe in ?
In whatever I can see and touch .
Ju [ classical
you 've probably heard this before .
It 's verdi 's " va , pensiero . "
Ju
Ju [ orchestra swells I
Hello , Mark ?
I found your sister 's letter . You left it at the academy .
Have you read it ? Well , you have to read it . It 's important .
Come over to my place right now . I want to tell you what happened to me .
J "
Ju
Jw [ Stops , resumes I
ju
J " [ Resuming , stopping I
- what 's going on ? - I don 't know .
Maybe there 's an overload on the wires .
Ju
Carlo ! Yes ?
Hey . Where 's the main fuse box ?
Jw " [ resumes I in the storeroom .
The door 's at the end of the hall . But don 't go there .
Don 't worry . I just want to check the fuses .
All right . But keep talking , so I know where you are . Ju
I will .
Carlo !
- Where are you ? - In the storeroom . I found the fuse box .
I 'll be right there . I 'm afraid .
Carlo !
Ju " [ resumes I
Carlo ! Carlo ! What 's happening ? J " [ Stopping , resuming I
just a second . I fixed it now , I think .
Jw " [ resumes I you see ?
Carlo ?
Ju [ Chorus swells I
No !
Ju
Ju [ Chorus swells I
Sara ?
Sara , it 's Mark .
" My dear brother Mark ,
the house I live in - 'the third key is under the soles of your shoes . '
kazanian . "
No . Nothing .
What about you ? You know what happened ?
I don 't know anything about it . She was already dead .
Hello ?
Hello ? Can you hear me ? It 's Mark .
Mark . Finally .
Talk louder , Rose . I can hardly hear you .
Did you get my letter ?
Yes . It came , but I didn 't get a chance to read it .
Why not ?
A lot 's happened .
Hello ?
L - I can 't hear a thing .
So , come to New York right away , Mark . If you care anything about me -
I can 't hear you . I don 't understand a thing . What 's going on , Rose ?
Promise you 'll come right away .
Sure . Of course I 'll come , but -
hello ?
Rose , hello .
Mark ?
J "
J " [ vocalizing continues I
Oh !
This goes to the usual place .
Uh , ma 'am ?
Yes ?
I " m Mark Elliot , Rose Elliot 's brother .
Oh , yes .
She 's in apartment 45 , fourth floor .
If you 'd like to go up , I have another set of keys .
Thanks .
Well , are you going up or not ?
Yes .
Fourth floor , to the left .
This is miss Elliot 's brother . He 's just arrived .
From Rome .
Ah ! Italy !
Thank you .
He 'd like to speak to you .
He does that whenever he has something to say .
His name is professor Arnold . He 's been quite ill for many years .
And you ? What do you do ?
Oh . I 'm a student . Musicology .
Oh ! Wonderful . A professor of toxicology .
We know two other young men who - no , no , no . It 's not toxicology .
Musicology . It 's got nothing to do with medicine .
What is it then ?
The study of music .
Oh , yes . Your sister 's involved in rather strange work too .
A pastime especially suited for women .
Good-bye .
" M-a-t-e-r . "
Rose ?
Rose .
Was that you ? Yes .
I was calling Rose . I saw the lights on and thought maybe she was back .
I 'm a friend . I live upstairs .
Rose isn 't back .
I 'm her brother Mark .
How did you do that ? I heard your voice coming from everywhere .
Oh . That 's something your sister and I discovered .
It 's our little secret . Look here .
See this hole in the wall ? There 's one going into my flat too .
It connects with open pipes in all the rooms .
When you speak into it , your voice becomes amplified .
This weird old building is full of secrets like that .
Would you like to come in ?
All right . But just for a moment .
No , no , don 't close it .
Someone 's coming to get me for the phone call .
My name is Elise Stallone Van adler .
I 've been living here for five years-alone .
My husband 's job keeps him traveling all the time .
I can 't travel with him because ... I 'm not well .
What 's strange is that Rose knew I was coming .
L - I thought she 'd be here waiting for me .
I can 't understand why she 's not back yet .
What kind of people live in a building like this ?
There aren 't many tenants .
A lot of the apartments are empty .
What I mean is - is there anyone special ?
I - I don 't know how to explain it ,
but Rose mentioned something in a letter .
All I know is that this building used to belong to a rich old eccentric .
They closed it down after he died , but eventually an investment company took it over .
Who 's kazanian ?
He 's a bookseller and antique dealer who owns the shop next door .
Rose buys a lot of rare books from him .
He also -
Excuse me .
You 're wanted on the telephone , madam .
All right . I 'm coming .
See you tomorrow , Mark .
Did madame cut herself ?
No , no , it 's paint , not blood .
Who 's there ?
Ow !
Damn cats .
What was the dosage this time ?
The first was 200 milligrams .
The second , 400 .
That 's the most you can take .
Shall I prepare your bath ?
Thank you .
Blood .
Your bath is ready , madame .
Good night . I 'll see you in the morning .
Good night . I hope you rest well .
Shh .
I 'm sure I stepped on blood .
Did you notice the door handle was broken ?
Yes , I did . I want to tell you something .
I used to wonder about Rose 's ravings .
Her nervousness , her fear of death .
The myth of the three mothers .
What 's that ?
She has a fixation .
Three Latin names -
mater suspiriorum , the mother of sighs .
Mater lacrimarum , the mother of tears .
And mater tenebrarum , the mother of darkness .
Rose read about them in an old book ,
and she talks as if it were a true story .
Rose thinks that someone living in this building -
no , I can 't explain it . She 'll have to tell you .
Such strange , impossible things .
She 's convinced that this building is in some way connected with those three mothers .
She mentioned an architect . Marelli or varelli-an Italian name .
I don 't know what the connection is aside from that .
But I too have begun to feel very nervous and uneasy lately .
It 's as if I were constantly being watched .
And at times , I think I actually feel a presence ,
as if someone were in the room with me .
I suppose the doctors are right . I am a nervous wreck . I need a lot of rest .
Did you hear that laugh ?
What laugh ? I don 't know .
It sounded like-you were right .
It really is blood . Come look .
Where does this door lead to ? To the service entrance .
But nobody ever uses it .
Well , somebody 's been through here . I 'm going to go look .
Do you want to come ? No . I 'll wait here . I 'm scared .
Okay .
Mark .
Mark !
Mark ! Where are you ?
Mark ?
Answer me !
Open the door , please !
Oh ! No ! No !
Help me . I 'm sick .
My heart .
He says it 's his heart .
Then he needs some heart medicine .
Oh , god , I feel awful .
Drink this now . You 'll feel better .
My sister Rose-where is she ?
Why doesn 't she come back ?
Let 's take him up to the apartment .
[ Gasping I where is she ?
Ugh .
Elise ?
Elise , it 's Mark . Can you hear me ?
Elise , it 's Mark .
Elise .
It 's disgusting . There must be dozens of them .
They walk right into my shop .
Last night , one of them scratched me and broke an expensive statue .
I 'm telling you . This is the very last time .
I 'll go to the police or to the board of health .
I want all of those damn cats away from here .
Do as you please , Mr. kazanian .
Ah , good morning .
I see you 're well again , Mr. Elliot .
Yes . I can 't even remember what happened to me last night .
You weren 't feeling well . It was your heart .
But I don 't have heart problems . We gave you some heart medicine all the same .
Who was that man ? That gimp ?
His name is kazanian . He 's got the antique shop .
Well , thank you . And thank you very much for last night .
A pleasure .
Mr. kazanian . Hmm ? Yes ?
I " m Mark Elliot , Rose 's brother . I-1 think you know her .
She bought some books from me .
Do you know her well ? No . Why ?
No one 's seen her for the last two days . I was hoping -
now look here . I just sell books to her . That 's all .
What kind of books ?
Old editions , that sort of thing .
If you can 't find her , why don 't you do what people usually do ?
Such as ?
Call the hospitals or the police .
I 've already done that . They don 't know a thing .
Does this mean anything to you ?
" The key is under the soles of your shoes " ?
What 's that , a riddle ?
I 'm not good at riddles .
How long have you been here ?
Since yesterday .
Ah . You know what ?
There 's going to be an eclipse of the moon tonight .
Oh , I didn 't know . Uh-huh .
It 's been 46 years since we 've had a total eclipse around here .
I heard them talking about it on television a little while ago .
You ought to watch . It ought to be interesting .
Okay , I 'll watch .
You 'll like it a lot .
Good-bye , Mr. Elliot .
Good-bye .
Ah .
There you are .
That 's a nice cat .
Yeah .
Come along .
Ah . Nice .
Huh .
You don 't want to leave , huh ?
Come on ! Sink , damn you !
My crutch !
Oh , god !
Help !
God !
Help me !
Get off me !
Oh , my god !
The rats are eating me !
Help !
Help me ! For Christ 's sake ! Please , god , somebody -
they 're eating me alive !
[ Groanin help ! ¢
Help ! Help !
They 're eating me alive !
Help ! The rats are eating me alive ! Help me ! Help !
God , help me !
Come here . Look at this .
Oh ! All that stuff .
La comtesse , that bitch .
She thought she 'd hidden it , so no one could find it .
I spent a good 15 minutes looking for it .
You 've been drinking . Not a drop .
I can smell it all over you .
I said I haven 't .
All right .
Now run upstairs and give her husband a call .
- Know where to find him at this hour ? - Mm-hmm .
Tell him la comtesse left all of a sudden and took all her valuables with her .
What if the bitch comes back ?
Don 't worry . She won 't be back .
How can you be so sure ? Let 's say she does come back .
I told you . She 's not coming back .
You just take care of calling her husband .
Now it 's our turn to enjoy life .
Now we are going to live it up like the comtesse Elise ...
And all the other rich bastards .
Who 's there ?
John .
John ?
[ Shutters banging I
Wh-what was that line ?
" Under the soles of your shoes . "
" The key is under the soles of your shoes . "
Mater tenebrarum , mater lacrimarum , mater suspiriorum .
[ Continues speaking Latin I
J " [ operatic rock I
J mater suspiriorum jt
j lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum j
j domine , domine j
ju
J mater suspiriorum j
j lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum j
j mater , mater suspiriorum jt
j lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum j
j domine , domine j
ju
J "
J lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum , tenebrarum j
ju
J "
J lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum j
j mater , mater suspiriorum jt
j lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum j
j "
Ju
J
You 've found the way down , I see .
And now I suppose ... You know who I am .
No , I don 't .
When I lived in London many years ago , I called myself varelli .
I use another name these days ...
To be forgotten .
Are you surprised to hear my voice ?
I can speak only with this .
I built the houses for the three mothers -
houses which became their eyes and ears .
Then I buried myself here .
This building has become my body .
Its bricks , my cells , its passageways , my veins .
And its horror , my very heart .
M-my sister-where is my sister ?
Come nearer . They should not hear you .
She 's the cruelest of them all .
The mother of shadows .
Come closer .
You can 't be afraid of a man who can hardly move .
A little closer , so I can whisper .
I may be dying now ,
but nothing will change .
They don 't want anything to be different .
I 'm not the master .
I am just a slave .
Who is it ? Who lives in this damned house ?
Someone who is waiting .
But who ?
You are being watched .
But to them ...
We are nothing but dust .
J "
Ju
It 's on fire .
It 's all going to burn down ,
just like before .
We have to get out of this place .
You can 't leave !
Your journey has come to an end .
Everything around you will become dark ,
and someone will take your hand .
You 'll be pleased , not unhappy .
You 'll enjoy moments of incredible brightness .
You think it 's magic .
No . I 'm not a magician .
Now we have to hurry , because we still have to pass through a number of strange phases , and you 'll change .
You were looking for me , just like your sister .
This is what you wanted . I 'm coming to get you !
Tell me who you are !
The three mothers .
Haven 't you understood ?
Mater tenebrarum .
Mater lacrimarum .
Mater suspiriorum .
But men call us by a single name -
a name which strikes fear into everyone 's heart .
They call us ... death !
Death !
Get ' em out of here !
Get me a unit around the back immediately !
Get them out of the space and send more equipment !
Get everybody back !
I need medics !
J " [ operatic rock I
J mater suspiriorum jt
j lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum j
j domine , domine j
ju
J mater suspiriorum j
j lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum j
j mater , mater suspiriorum jt
j lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum j
j domine , domine j
ju
J "
J lacrimarum j
j tenebrarum , tenebrarum j
ju
J